(upbeat music)
- Hello, English learners,
welcome back to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- And I'm Erica.
- And we're bringing you the final
lesson of our job interview series.
- That's right, and in this lesson, we're
gonna be focusing on two very, very common,
but sometimes difficult questions.
- Okay, so we've talked about preparing
for the job interview in part one.
Part two, we talked about
educational background
and work experience, and in part
three, what are we gonna be looking at?
- We're gonna be looking at two questions.
Why we should hire you,
and your greatest weakness.
- Okay, so these are the
classic common questions
that you'll get at a
job interview, right?
- That's right, so
why don't we just get
started and we'll take
a listen to the dialogue
and see how our interviewee
handles these questions.
(upbeat music)
- Very good.
- Oh, I have a couple of final questions.
- I hope they're not too hard.
(laughing)
- Oil, why should we hire you?
- I think that I would be a
perfect fit in this company.
I have a unique combination of strong
technical acumen without standing soft skills.
I excel at building strong,
long-term consumer relationships.
For example, when I headed
the customer support department
in my previous company, our team resolved
about 70% of our customers' problems.
I decided that we needed better information
and technical preparation on our products.
So after, I implemented a
series of training sessions
in coordination with
our technical department,
we were able to solve 90%
of our customers' issues.
Given the opportunity, I could bring
this kind of success to this company.
- Whoa, impressive.
So what would you consider
to be your greatest weakness?
- To be honest, I struggle with
organization and time management.
Punctuality has never
been a strength in mind.
I find it hard to organize
my time effectively.
I've actually addressed
this weakness recently
by attending a workshop
on efficient time management.
It helped me a lot by
providing me with great insights
on how to get organized
and use my time efficiently.
So I think I'm getting better now.
(laughing)
Great.
Well, let me tell you that I am
very pleased with this interview.
We are shortlisting our
candidates this week.
And next week, we will inform
our shortlisted candidates
of the day and time for a
second interview with our CEO.
- Great, thanks a lot.
I hope to hear from you.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)
- Well, our interviewee is doing very well,
but I think he had a little
bit too many beans or chillies.
- Oh my gosh, this is probably the
most embarrassing thing I can think of.
- But he doesn't say
anything, so I don't know.
Maybe he should have said,
oh, pardon me, excuse me.
- I don't know.
I don't know, it's a controversy.
- Yeah, okay, but what
isn't a controversy is the
language 'cause there's
some great stuff in here.
- All right.
So let's take a look at the
language in language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
All right, we've got some great
phrases and words for you to use
when you're talking
about what sort of benefits
and skills and experience and
expertise you can bring to a company.
- Okay, the first thing
that he said, and it's a
very interesting word
he said, technical acumen.
- Technical acumen.
- Acumen, acumen.
- This is a really hard word.
What is acumen?
- It's basically insight and understanding
and the ability to make
good and difficult decisions.
- Okay, so he has a very
strong technical acumen.
- So a strong insight or
understanding of technical issues.
- Okay, or I can change it and may
say, I have a very strong business acumen.
- Exactly, these are the two most
common ways that this word is used.
Technical acumen, business acumen.
- Okay, great.
Now let's take a look at another word,
which is very interesting
'cause everybody knows it.
- Yes, Excel.
- Excel.
- Now Excel is, of course, the
software that you use, right?
- Yeah, but here it's a verb, meaning,
to be really, really good at something.
- Right, to be the best, maybe.
- Yeah.
- To Excel at something.
- Yes, so I Excel at cooking.
- All right, so Excel, you are the best.
- I mean, that's not really gonna help me
in a job interview, but
the next word might.
(laughs)
- Head, head.
Well, in the dialogue, we heard
it as headed in the past, right?
- Yeah, that's right.
He headed the customer support department.
- So I think this is very,
a great, I think this is a
great word to use when you
were saying I was the leader.
- Mm-hmm.
- I was the main person in charge.
- Yeah, the manager.
So this is a nice verb to use to show
that you were leading something.
- Okay.
- Okay, now for the next word.
- Struggle.
- To struggle.
- So what does struggle mean?
- It means that you have
difficulty doing something.
- So it's hard for you.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- For example, when I was in
school, I struggled with math.
- Okay, and now I struggle with Chinese.
- Exactly, so to have a hard time.
- Yeah, why don't we hear a couple
of examples of how this word is used?
- Example one.
- We're really struggling
to reach our sales target.
- Example two.
- Yeah, to be honest, I do
struggle with time management.
- Example three.
- The teacher farted in class and
I really had to struggle not to last.
- Okay, so great examples.
Let's move on to our next word.
Punctuality.
- Punctuality.
- Okay, so to be punctual.
- It means to be on time, always.
- Always.
So punctuality would be the noun form.
- Right, so the condition or
the state of always being on time.
- Right, so punctuality to be punctual.
- Yeah, in our interviewee,
struggles with punctuality.
- Right, like me.
- I guess you guys have
something in common.
- We do.
- Now, he has a problem with punctuality,
but he said he has addressed this weakness.
- Yes, to address address.
- Now, if you notice, it's
spelled the same way as address.
- That's right.
- But you pronounce it differently.
- So the verb address has the
stress on the second syllable.
- Okay, address.
- Yes.
- And that means to deal with.
- To deal with the problem.
- Yeah, to acknowledge the problem.
- And to try and solve it.
- Okay, so different from your
home address where you live.
- Yeah, and there the
stress is on the first syllable.
- Address.
- Right.
- Very good.
Okay, so let's listen to this
dialogue one more time,
and then we'll come back and
talk about these two questions.
Greatest weakness, and
why should we hire you?
(upbeat music)
- Very good.
- Oh, I have a couple of final questions.
- I hope they're not too hard.
(laughing)
- Oil, why should we hire you?
- I think that I would be a
perfect fit in this company.
I have a unique combination
of strong technical
acumen without standing
soft skills, you know?
I excel at building strong,
long-term consumer relationships.
For example, when I headed the customer
support department in my previous company,
our team resolved about 70%
of our customers' problems.
I decided that we needed better information
and technical preparation on our products.
So after, I implemented a
series of training sessions
in coordination with
our technical department.
We were able to solve
90% of our customers' issues.
Given the opportunity, I could bring
this kind of success to this company.
(grunting)
- Impressive.
So what would you consider
to be your greatest weakness?
- To be honest, I
struggle with organization
and time management punctuality
has never been a strength in mind.
I find it hard to organize
my time effectively.
I've actually addressed
this weakness recently
by attending a workshop
on efficient time management.
It helped me a lot by
providing me with great insights
on how to get organized
and use my time efficiently.
So I think I'm getting better now.
(chuckling)
Great.
Well, let me tell you that I am
very pleased with this interview.
We are short-listing
our candidates this week.
And next week, we will inform
our short-listed candidates
of the day and time for a
second interview with our CEO.
- Great, thanks a lot.
I hope to hear from you.
- Goodbye.
(upbeat music)
- All right, Marco, well, this classic
question, why should we hire you?
I think you'll hear it in many,
many different interviews.
And how did he deal with it here?
- Well, the first thing
that he said is very,
very important because
they were asking you why.
So your immediate reaction
would be to answer with
because or I think that,
but there's a different way
of approaching it, which is
a little bit more professional.
He said, I think that I would
be a perfect fit in this company.
- I think I would be a
perfect fit in this company.
That's how he started his answer.
And then he explained why.
- So this sounds really strong, doesn't it?
- Yeah, basically it just makes
you seem to be very confident
and puts you like you are
already part of the company.
- Mm-hmm.
- So this is a great way
to start off this question,
but you gotta follow this
up with some information.
So what kind of information
should you be given?
- Well, like we talked about in your
work experience, the same thing goes here.
What do you have to offer to this company?
What special skills or insights
or experience can you bring
that would help us?
- Yeah, that nobody else can bring.
- Exactly.
So again, you have to start
talking about your strengths
and your previous experience,
but with examples, right?
- Very, very specific examples.
And whenever you can, throw in some numbers
or some specific successes
that you have had.
- Exactly.
And once you've talked about these things,
you can close off this answer by saying,
given the opportunity, I could bring
this kind of success to this company.
- Given the opportunity, I could bring
- So that is just like a magical sentence,
saying like, if you give me the chance,
I will demonstrate how good I am
and how I can help this company.
- Yes, a really, really
strong closing argument.
- Yes.
So that's the way you
should more or less approach
that question, right?
- All right, but let's
turn now to the classic,
classic question, your
greatest weakness.
- What is your greatest weakness?
- When you get this
question, be sure to not
say, my greatest weakness
is, I work too much.
My greatest weakness is, I'm a workaholic.
- Right, or, or was it,
or I am perfectionist?
- Yeah, these, we can
see right through these.
I mean, they're too
obvious and they're too silly.
I mean, everyone has a weakness, so don't
try and turn it around into a strength.
I just don't think that's a good idea.
- Okay, so yeah, be sure to
stay away from these answers.
But you can say anything, like in this
case, he has a problem with being on time.
- Yeah, so be honest, say what
one of your greatest weaknesses are.
But the key to making
this weakness look good
is saying what you are
doing to solve this weakness.
- Exactly, so really be truthful.
Tell the interviewer
what you're not good at,
'cause there's obviously
something that you're not good at.
- Exactly, so you can
say, I am usually late,
but I am getting more
organized, I'm doing a seminar.
I, you know, let the interviewer know that
you are trying to improve this weakness.
- Exactly, and be sure to also
think about your strength, right?
- Yeah, be prepared to answer the
question, what is your greatest strength?
- So, and again, when you're
talking about your strengths,
be sure it's something more specific
than saying, oh, I'm very responsible.
- Yeah, you know, want
to be as specific as you can.
And again, give those examples, give
those successes, give those numbers.
- Right, exactly, so think about your
weaknesses, think about your strengths.
If you don't know them, ask
people to ask your colleagues
or ask your friends, what do
you think is my greatest strength?
Maybe you're a funny
person, that's a strength.
- Yes.
- Okay.
- Well, remember, there are three
parts to this interviewing series,
and you can find them on
our website at englishpod.com.
- Right, come to our
website englishpod.com.
You can look at all of these three lessons,
and I hope they are really helpful.
And of course, if you have
any questions or comments,
or maybe you'd like a little bit more
of this interview series, let us know.
- All right, guys, well,
thanks for listening.
Good luck in your interviews,
and until next time, goodbye.
(upbeat music)